Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 62: Connective Tissue Disorders.
Immune-Mediated Connective Tissue Diseases Systemic Lupus Erythematosus Antiphospholipid Syndrome Rheumatoid Arthritis Systemic Sclerosis—Scleroderma Vasculitis Syndromes Inflammatory Myopathies Hereditary Connective Tissue Disorders References Connective tissue disorders, also termed collagen vascular disorders, have two basic underlying causes.
First are the immune-complex diseases, in which deposition of immune complexes causes connective tissue damage.
Because these manifest by sterile inflammation—predominantly of the skin, joints, blood vessels, and kidneys—they are referred to as rheumatic diseases.
Many of these immune-complex diseases are more prevalent in women, and systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) and rheumatoid arthritis are examples.
Second are the inherited disorders that involve bone, skin, cartilage, blood vessels, and basement membranes.
These include Marfan syndrome, osteogenesis imperfecta, and Ehlers-Danlos syndrome.
Immune-Mediated Connective Tissue Diseases.
These disorders can be separated into those associated with and those without autoantibody formation.
The rheumatoid factor is an autoantibody found in many autoimmune inflammatory conditions such as SLE, rheumatoid arthritis, systemic sclerosis (scleroderma), mixed connective tissue disease, dermatomyositis, polymyositis, and various vasculitis syndromes.
Instead, the RF-seronegative spondyloarthropathies are strongly associated with expression of the antigen termed human leukocyte antigen B27 (HLA-B27).
These include ankylosing spondylitis, psoriatic arthritis, Reiter disease, and other arthritis syndromes.
The normal immunosuppression of pregnancy that allows and is essential for successful engraftment of fetal and placental tissues may mitigate activity in some of these syndromes.
First, estrogens upregulate and androgens downregulate T-cell response, and progesterone is immunosuppressive (Abdul Hussain, 2020; Robinson, 2012).
Second, pregnancy induces a predominance of T2 helper cells compared with cytokine-producing T1 helper cells .
These changes are discussed in detail in Chapter 4 (p. 61).
However, active immune-mediated disease may contribute to obstetrical complications .
One longitudinal cohort study found that unrecognized autoimmune systemic rheumatic disorders are associated with significant risk for preeclampsia and fetal-growth restriction .
In this study, the prevalence of unrecognized systemic rheumatic diseases approximated 0.3 percent, and preeclampsia or fetal-growth restriction complicated 25 percent of these pregnancies.
Last, some immune-mediated diseases may be either caused or activated as a result of prior pregnancies.
To explain, fetal cells and cell-free DNA are detectable in maternal blood beginning early in pregnancy (Simpson, 2013; Waldorf, 2008).
Fetal cell microchimerism is the persistence of fetal cells in the maternal circulation and in organs following pregnancy.
These fetal cells may become engrafted in maternal tissues and stimulate production of autoantibodies.
Evidence for this includes fetal stem cells engrafted in tissues in women with autoimmune thyroiditis and systemic sclerosis (Jimenez, 2005; Srivatsa, 2001).
Such microchimerism has also been described in women with SLE and those with rheumatoid arthritis– associated HLA alleles (da Silva, 2016; Lee, 2010).
Conversely, engrafted maternal cells may provoke autoimmune conditions in a woman’s offspring (Stevens, 2016; Ye, 2012).
Systemic Lupus Erythematosus.
This autoimmune disease has an intricate pathogenesis that results from interactions between susceptibility genes and environmental factors .
Tissue-binding autoantibodies and immune complexes that are directed at one or more nuclear components lead to cellular and organ damage .
In addition to this B-cell antibody production, immunosuppression is impaired, including regulatory T-cell function .
Some autoantibodies produced in patients with SLE are shown in Table 62-1.
Most patients have autoantibodies for many years before
clinical disease manifests.
TABLE 62-1.
Some Autoantibodies Produced in Patients with Systemic Lupus Erythematosus Genetic influences are implicated, and the concordance is higher with monozygotic compared with dizygotic twins—25 versus 2 percent, respectively.
Moreover, the frequency in patients with one affected family member is 10 percent.
The relative risk of disease rises if the “autoimmunity gene” on chromosome 16 that predisposes to SLE, rheumatoid arthritis, Crohn disease, and psoriasis is inherited.
However, susceptibility genes such as HLA-DR3, STAT4, APOL1, FCGR3A, and DNAse1 explain only a portion of the genetic heritability (Hahn, 2018; Yang, 2013).
Interestingly, maternal exposure to fetal genes elevates susceptibility to SLE development.
A case-control study found that a child’s HLA-DRB1 genotype raises the risk of SLE in the mother .
In contrast, neonatal lupus has been reported in an infant conceived via oocyte donor to a mother with autoimmune disease with circulating anti-Ro and anti-La antibodies .
# Clinical Manifestations and Diagnosis.
Almost 90 percent of SLE cases develop in women, and it more commonly affects African-American women compared with other populations (Izmirly, 2017; Stojan, 2018).
Its prevalence in those of childbearing age approximates 1 case in 500 .
Accordingly, the disease is encountered relatively frequently during pregnancy.
SLE notoriously varies in its presentation, course, and outcome .
Findings may be confined initially to one organ system, and others become involved later.
Instead, the disease may first be multisystem.
Frequent findings are malaise, fever, arthritis, rash, pleuropericarditis, photosensitivity, anemia, and cognitive dysfunction.
At least half of patients have renal involvement.
SLE is also associated with declines in attention, memory, and reasoning (Hahn, 2018; Kozora, 2008).
Table 62-3.
Clinical Criteria for Classification of Systemic Lupus Erythematosus Identification of antinuclear antibodies (ANA) is the best screening test, however, a positive result is not specific for SLE.
Low titers can be found in normal individuals, other autoimmune diseases, acute viral infections, and chronic inflammatory processes.
Several drugs also can cause a positive reaction.
Antibodies to double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) and to Smith (Sm) antigens are relatively specific for SLE, whereas other antibodies are not .
Although hundreds of autoantibodies have been described in SLE, only a few have been shown to participate in tissue injury .
Microarray profiles are being developed for more accurate diagnosis .
Chronic anemia develops frequently, and there may be leukopenia and thrombocytopenia.
Proteinuria and casts are found in the half of patients with glomerular lesions.
Lupus nephritis can also cause renal insufficiency, which is more common if there are antiphospholipid antibodies .
Other laboratory findings include false-positive syphilis serology, prolonged partial thromboplastin time, and higher rheumatoid factor levels.
Increased serum D-dimer concentrations often follow a flare or infection, but unexplained persistent elevations are associated with a high risk for thrombosis .
The diagnostic criteria for SLE are listed in Table 62-3.
If any four or more of the 11 clinical criteria are present, serially or simultaneously, the diagnosis is made.
Importantly, numerous drugs can induce a lupus-like syndrome.
These include proton-pump inhibitors, thiazide diuretics, antifungals, antihypertensives, chemotherapeutics, statins, and antiepileptics.
Drug-induced lupus is rarely associated with glomerulonephritis and usually regresses when the medication is discontinued .
Table 62-2.
Some Clinical Manifestations of Systemic Lupus Erythematosus # Lupus and Pregnancy.
In a metaanalysis of nearly 9 million pregnancies, the incidence of lupus approximated 1 case in 900 births .
During pregnancy, lupus improves in a third of women, remains unchanged in a third, and worsens in the remaining third.
Thus, in any pregnancy, the clinical condition can worsen or flare without
warning .
In a cohort of 13,555 pregnant women with SLE, the maternal mortality rate was 325 per 100,000 .
Maternal deaths invariably occur in those with active disease .
Women with SLE are at greater risk for thrombotic complications, infection, postpartum hemorrhage, and blood transfusion.
He and Wei (2020) reported increased risks of adverse pregnancy outcomes in women with SLE compared with unaffected women .
Table 62-4.
Risk of Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes in Women with Systemic Lupus Erythematosus During the past several decades, pregnancy outcomes in women with SLE have improved remarkably.
For most women with inactive or mild/moderate disease activity, pregnancy outcomes are relatively favorable .
Women who have confined cutaneous lupus do not usually have adverse outcomes .
However, newly diagnosed SLE during pregnancy tends to be severe .
In general, pregnancy outcome is best in women for whom: (1) lupus activity has been quiescent for at least 6 months before conception; (2) lupus nephritis manifest by proteinuria or renal dysfunction is absent; (3) neither antiphospholipid syndrome nor lupus anticoagulant are detected; and (4) superimposed preeclampsia does not develop (Peart, 2014; Petri, 2020a; Stojan, 2012).
# Lupus Nephritis.
Active nephritis is associated with adverse pregnancy outcomes, although these have improved substantially and especially if disease remains in remission (Stojan, 2012; Wagner, 2009).
Of complications, women with renal disease have a high incidence of gestational hypertension and preeclampsia.
Of 137 women with SLE reported by Rodrigues and colleagues (2019), 27 percent of gravidas with preexisting renal disease developed preeclampsia compared with only 16 percent of those without underlying renal disease.
In a review of 309 pregnancies complicated by lupus nephritis, 30 percent suffered a flare, and 40 percent of these had associated renal insufficiency .
The maternal mortality rate was 1.3 percent.
These findings were corroborated in a subsequent prospective study .
In addition, a third of the 113 pregnancies were delivered preterm.
Compared with women without nephritis or with inactive nephritis, those with active nephritis have a significantly increased incidence of maternal and fetal complications (Rodrigues, 2019; Wagner, 2009).
The higher the histological class, the greater the risk.
Most recommend continuation of immunosuppressive therapy for nephritis during pregnancy.
Hydroxychloroquine, cyclosporine, azathioprine, and tacrolimus are permissible in pregnancy (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019b; Parikh, 2020).
New-onset nephritis or severe renal flare is treated aggressively with tacrolimus, and consideration is given to adding intravenous corticosteroids, immunosuppressive drugs, or intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG) therapy (Maynard, 2019; Parikh, 2020).
# Lupus Versus Preeclampsia-Eclampsia.
Chronic hypertension complicates up to 30 percent of pregnancies in women with SLE .
Preeclampsia is common, and in those with nephritis or antiphospholipid antibodies, superimposed preeclampsia is encountered even more often and earlier (Bertsias, 2008; Dong, 2020).
Preeclampsia and SLE flares share features of hypertension, proteinuria, edema, and renal function deterioration.
However, the management is distinct.
Lupus nephritis is treated with immunosuppression, and severe preeclampsia/eclampsia requires delivery.
It may be difficult, if not impossible, to discriminate a lupus flare with nephropathy from severe preeclampsia if the kidney is the only involved organ .
Serum uric acid and complement levels and dsDNA titers may aid in differentiating the two.
Last, central nervous system involvement with SLE may culminate in convulsions similar to those of eclampsia.
# Management During Pregnancy.
Care consists primarily of monitoring maternal clinical and laboratory status and fetal well-being.
Establishment of baseline renal disease and hematological values is important because pregnancy-induced laboratory changes later in gestation can resemble SLE disease
activity.
A 24-hour urine collection to assess proteinuria and serum creatinine level measurement determine initial renal function.
A complete blood count (CBC) identifies preexisting anemia, leukopenia, and thrombocytopenia.
Continued assessment of renal function and hematological parameters is undertaken each trimester unless symptoms develop.
In this event, measures are monthly .
For monitoring of SLE activity, various laboratory techniques have been recommended.
As just discussed, establishing baseline values will assist comparisons later in pregnancy.
Serum complement levels (C3 and C4) and dsDNA titers are drawn at the first prenatal care visit and when symptoms develop.
Serum complement levels are normally increased in pregnancy (Appendix, p. 1231).
Although falling or low C3 and C4 levels are more likely to be associated with active disease, higher levels provide no assurance against disease flare.
If symptoms develop, the combination of declining complement levels and rising dsDNA titers does indicate a lupus flare .
Women with SLE are also screened for antiphospholipid antibodies at the beginning of pregnancy.
Last, screening for anti-SS-A (antiRo) and anti-SS-B (anti-La) antibodies is recommended because of associated fetal complications described later.
The combination of serial hematological, rheumatological, and renal studies may detect changes in disease activity.
SLE-associated hemolysis is characterized by a positive Coombs test, anemia, reticulocytosis, and unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia.
Thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, or both may develop.
Chronic thrombocytopenia in early pregnancy may be due to antiphospholipid antibodies .
Later, thrombocytopenia may indicate preeclampsia.
The fetus also is closely observed for adverse effects such as growth restriction and oligohydramnios.
Sonographic evaluations are performed every 4 weeks beginning at 24 weeks’ gestation to assess for both.
Antepartum testing for fetal well-being is initiated in the third trimester and described in Chapter 20 (p. 392) (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021a,b).
Unless evidence of maternal or fetal compromise develops, pregnancy is allowed to progress to term.
# Pharmacological Treatment.
There is no cure for SLE, and complete remissions are rare.
Approximately a fourth of pregnant women have mild disease, which is not life threatening but may be disabling because of pain and fatigue.
Arthralgia and serositis can be managed by nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs (NSAIDs).
However, during pregnancy, chronic or large intermittent dosing is avoided due to related oligohydramnios or ductus arteriosus closure .
Antimalarials reduce dermatitis, arthritis, and fatigue .
Although these agents cross the placenta, hydroxychloroquine (Plaquenil) does not appear to cause congenital malformations .
Most recommend continuation during pregnancy because therapy interruption can precipitate a flare (Marder, 2019; Petri, 2019).
For those not previously using hydroxychloroquine, others favor initiation in the first trimester because its use is associated with an 85-percent reduction in the risk of having a small-for-gestational-age neonate .
Also, it lowers the risk of fetal congenital heart block by 50 percent in women with anti-SSA antibodies.
Low-dose aspirin can be used throughout gestation.
Severe disease is managed with corticosteroids such as prednisone, 1 to 2 mg/kg/d orally or methylprednisolone, 1000 mg given intravenously over 90 minutes daily for 3 days .
After the disease is controlled, this dose is tapered to a daily morning dose of 10 to 15 mg. Corticosteroid therapy can lead to gestational diabetes.
During labor, delivery, and postpartum, corticosteroids in “stress doses” are given to women who take these drugs chronically or who have done so recently.
This augmented dose reflects a normal adrenal response, and one option on admission for delivery is hydrocortisone, 100 mg, given IV every 8 hours for 48 hours.
Tacrolimus, rituximab, and IVIG therapy also have been used to treat lupus flares .
These are
usually reserved for lupus nephritis or disease that is corticosteroid resistant.
Azathioprine has a good safety record during pregnancy (Hahn, 2018; Petri, 2019).
Its recommended daily oral dose is 2 mg/kg.
Teratogenic medications to be avoided include mycophenolate mofetil, methotrexate, and cyclophosphamide (Briggs, 2022; Hahn, 2018).
However, cyclophosphamide can be considered in the second or third trimester for severe disease .
In nonpregnant subjects, antihypertensive therapy often includes an angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor or an angiotensin-receptor blocker.
For pregnancy, these should be changed to safer fetal options such as calcium-channel blockers, alpha methyldopa, or labetalol .
# Perinatal Mortality and Morbidity.
Adverse perinatal outcome rates are significantly elevated in pregnancies complicated by SLE.
Among these are preterm delivery, fetal-growth restriction, stillbirth, and neonatal lupus syndrome (He, 2020; Phansenee, 2018).
Perinatal outcome rates worsen in women with active disease, significant proteinuria, or renal impairment and in those with chronic hypertension, preeclampsia, or both .
Adverse outcomes are also more common in women with neuropsychiatric lupus (de Jesus, 2017).
Reasons at least partially responsible for adverse fetal consequences include decidual vasculopathy with placental infarction and decreased perfusion .
# Neonatal Lupus Syndrome.
This is characterized by newborn skin lesions—lupus dermatitis; various hematological and systemic derangements; and occasionally congenital heart block .
Cutaneous manifestations can be present in 30 to 40 percent of infants and appear at 4 to 6 weeks of age .
These are usually associated with anti-SS-A and SS-B antibodies, and up to 50 percent of women with SLE are positive for these .
Thrombocytopenia and hepatic involvement are seen in 5 to 10 percent of affected infants.
In a review of outcomes in 128 infants born to women with lupus, 16 percent developed cutaneous lupus and 26 percent showed hematological abnormalities and elevated transaminase levels .
Cutaneous lupus, thrombocytopenia, and autoimmune hemolysis are transient and clear within a few months .
In subsequent offspring, the recurrence risk for neonatal lupus may approach 25 percent .
The only maternal treatment that lowers the risk of neonatal lupus is hydroxychloroquine (Izmirly, 2020; Petri, 2019).
# Congenital Heart Block.
Fetal and neonatal heart block results from diffuse myocarditis and fibrosis in the region between the atrioventricular (AV) node and bundle of His.
Natural killer cells have been detected in fetal myocytes .
Congenital heart block develops almost exclusively in fetuses of women with antibodies to the SS-A or SS-B antigens .
Even in the presence of such antibodies, the incidence of fetal myocarditis is only 2 to 3 percent (Bramham, 2012; Lateef, 2017).
However, it rises to 20 percent with a prior affected child.
The cardiac lesion is permanent, and a pacemaker is generally necessary.
Long-term prognosis is poor.
Of 325 infants with cardiac neonatal lupus, nearly 20 percent died, and of these, a third were stillborn .
Another autoimmune disease, Sjögren syndrome, also is associated with fetal heart block (Brito-Zerón, 2020).
Maternal administration of corticosteroids, plasma exchange, or IVIG therapy does not reduce the risk of congenital heart block.
For women with anti-SS-B and anti-SS-A antibodies, fetal cardiac monitoring is performed between 18 and 26 weeks’ gestation.
Maternal corticosteroid administration for treatment of fetal congenital heart block is controversial and discussed further in Chapter 19 (p. 369).
This therapy to treat fetal heart block has not been studied in randomized trials.
However, some evidence derives from fetuses exposed to their mother’s corticosteroid treatment for SLE and shows that exposure may mitigate fetal myocarditis.
Specifically, Shinohara and coworkers (1999) reported no cases of heart block in 26 neonates whose mothers received corticosteroids before 16 weeks’ gestation as part of SLE
maintenance therapy.
By contrast, 15 of 61 neonates with heart block were born to women in whom corticosteroid therapy was begun after 16 weeks for an SLE exacerbation.
Maternal hydroxychloroquine therapy is associated with a lower incidence of fetal heart block, especially in those with a prior affected child (Izmirly, 2010, 2020).
# Long-term Prognosis and Contraception.
The survival rate for women with SLE is 95 percent at 5 years, 90 percent at 10 years, and 78 percent at 20 years .
Infection, lupus flares, end-organ failure, hypertension, stroke, and cardiovascular disease account for most deaths.
In general, women with SLE and chronic vascular or renal disease may limit family size because of morbidity associated with the disease and greater risks for adverse perinatal outcomes.
For contraception, combination oral contraceptives did not increase the incidence of lupus flares in two large multicenter trials (Petri, 2005; Sánchez-Guerrero, 2005).
Notably, comorbid antiphospholipid antibodies are a contraindication to estrogen-containing methods .
Progestin-only implants and injections provide effective contraception with no known effects on lupus flare rates .
Data do not support the concern that intrauterine device use and immunosuppressive therapy lead to higher infection rates in these patients.
Tubal sterilization may be advantageous and is performed with greatest safety postpartum or whenever SLE is quiescent .
Antiphospholipid Syndrome.
This is an autoantibody-mediated acquired thrombophilia that predisposes to recurrent thrombosis or pregnancy morbidity .
Specifically, antiphospholipid syndrome (APS) is diagnosed in women with persistently positive serum tests for antiphospholipid antibodies (APAs) plus arterial and/or venous thromboses or obstetrical morbidity.
APAs include lupus anticoagulant, anticardiolipin antibody, and anti-β2 glycoprotein-I antibody.
Phospholipids are the main lipid constituents of cell and organelle membranes.
Certain proteins in plasma associate noncovalently with these phospholipids.
APAs are directed against these phospholipids or these phospholipid-binding proteins (Garcia, 2018; Giannakopoulos, 2013).
This antibody group may be of immunoglobulin G (IgG), IgM, and IgA classes, alone or in combination.
APAs are most common with SLE, other connective tissue disorders, and APS.
That said, a small proportion of normal women and men have low levels of these antibodies.
The stimulus for autoantibody production is unclear, but it possibly is due to a preceding infection or another event that causes endothelial disruption.
The resulting pathophysiology is mediated by one or more of the following: (1) activation of various procoagulants, (2) inactivation of natural anticoagulants, (3) complement activation, and (4) inhibition of syncytiotrophoblast differentiation .
Clinically, these actions lead to vascular thromboses or to pregnancy morbidity.
Virtually every organ system may be affected.
Central nervous system involvement is one of the most prominent clinical manifestations.
In addition to cerebrovascular arterial or venous thrombotic events, psychiatric features and even multiple sclerosis can be present .
Renovascular involvement may lead to renal failure that can be difficult to differentiate from lupus nephritis (D’Cruz, 2009).
Peripheral and visceral thromboses also are features.
In one case, a puerpera developed a mesenteric vessel infarction and subsequent spontaneous cecal perforation .
Obstetrical complications encompass recurrent pregnancy loss and placental dysfunction reflected by fetal-growth restriction, stillbirth, early-onset preeclampsia, and preterm birth.
Treatment using aspirin, heparin, and close monitoring has increased live-birth rates to more than 70 percent in these women (Hamulyák, 2020; Schreiber, 2016).
A small proportion of these patients develop the catastrophic antiphospholipid antibody syndrome (CAPS) or Asherson syndrome.
This is defined as a rapidly progressive thromboembolic disorder simultaneously affecting three or more organ systems or tissues
Garcia, 2018; Schreiber, 2016).
It has a high mortality rate from activation of a cytokine storm.
In half of cases, a triggering event is identified.
# Specific Antiphospholipid Antibodies.
As mentioned, several antibodies in APS are directed against a specific phospholipid or a phospholipid-binding protein: 1. β2 glycoprotein-I, also known as apolipoprotein H, is a phospholipidbinding plasma protein that inhibits prothrombinase activity within platelets and prevents platelet aggregation .
Thus, its normal action is to limit procoagulant binding and thereby prevent coagulation cascade activation.
Logically, antibodies directed against this glycoprotein would reverse its anticoagulant activity and promote thrombosis.
This is important from an obstetrical viewpoint because β2 glycoprotein-I is expressed in high concentrations on the syncytiotrophoblast surface.
Complement activation may contribute to its pathogenesis (Avalos, 2009; Tsokos, 2011).
Teleologically, this seems appropriate because the decidua intuitively should be a critical area to prevent coagulation that might lead to intervillous space thrombosis.
2. Lupus anticoagulant (LAC) is a heterogeneous group of antibodies directed against phospholipid-binding proteins.
This antibody group induces prolongation in vitro of the prothrombin, partial thromboplastin, and Russell viper venom times.
Thus, paradoxically, this so-called anticoagulant is actually powerfully thrombotic in vivo.
This is the only APA that has been consistently associated with adverse pregnancy outcomes .
3. Anticardiolipin antibodies (ACAs) are directed against one of the many phospholipid cardiolipins found in mitochondrial membranes and platelets.
# Antibodies Against Natural Anticoagulants.
Some APAs are also directed against the natural anticoagulant proteins C and S.
Another is directed against the anticoagulant protein annexin V, which is expressed in high concentrations by syncytiotrophoblast .
Testing for these other antibodies is not recommended .
However, some studies have evaluated these nonconventional antiphospholipid antibodies in women who clinically meet APS criteria but do not have the classic antibody profile.
In one study, treatment of women who had these nonconventional antibodies offered some benefits, such as a lower pregnancy loss rate .
Clinical features shown in Table 62-5 provide indications for testing.
By international consensus, APS is diagnosed based on laboratory and clinical criteria (Table 11-4, p. 205).
First, one of two clinical criteria—which are vascular thrombosis or certain pregnancy morbidity—must be present.
With laboratory criteria, high IgG or IgM titers of ACA or anti-β2 glycoprotein-I or LAC positivity should be confirmed on two occasions 12 weeks apart.
The diagnosis can be further stratified based on the number of these tests that are positive.
Table 62-5.
Some Clinical Features of Antiphospholipid Syndrome Tests for LAC are nonspecific coagulation tests.
The partial thromboplastin time is generally prolonged because the anticoagulant interferes with conversion of prothrombin to thrombin in vitro.
The dilute Russell viper venom test is considered more specific.
Branch and Khamashta (2003) recommend conservative interpretation of results that are based on repeated tests from a reliable laboratory and that are consistent with each clinical case.
Only approximately 20 percent of patients with APS have a positive LAC assay alone.
Thus, ACA enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) testing also should be performed.
Efforts have been made to standardize ACA assays, however, these remain without international standards .
For each APS test, interlaboratory variation can be large, and agreement between commercial kits is poor.
# Pregnancy and Antiphospholipid Antibodies.
As many as 30 percent of patients with SLE have APAs.
In women without autoimmune diseases who have pregnancy complications, the prevalence of positive results with APA testing is 7 percent .
In women with elevated APA levels, and especially when LAC is identified, risks for
decidual vasculopathy, placental infarction, fetal-growth restriction, early-onset preeclampsia, and recurrent fetal death are increased .
Some of these women, like those with SLE, also have a high incidence of venous and arterial thromboses, cerebral thrombosis, hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, and pulmonary hypertension (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019a; Clowse, 2008).
In 191 LAC-negative women with APS, those with ACAs and β2-glycoprotein-I had significantly greater miscarriage rates than if either one alone was positive .
Women with higher titers tend to have more adverse outcomes (Alijotas-Reig, 2020; Gabbay-Benziv, 2018).
# Pregnancy Pathophysiology.
It is not precisely known how APAs cause damage, but it is likely that their actions are multifactorial.
Platelets may be damaged directly by APAs or indirectly by binding β2-glycoprotein-I, which causes platelets to be susceptible to aggregation .
One theory proposes that phospholipid-containing endothelial cell or syncytiotrophoblast membranes may be damaged directly by the APA or indirectly by antibody binding to either β2 glycoprotein-I or annexin V (Rand, 1997, 1998).
This prevents the cell membranes from protecting the syncytiotrophoblast and endothelium.
This exposes the basement membrane, to which damaged platelets can adhere and form a thrombus.
Pierro and colleagues (1999) reported that APAs decreased decidual production of the vasodilating prostaglandin E2.
Diminished protein C or S activity and greater prothrombin activation also may be contributory .
Evidence supports that thrombosis with APS stems from activation of the tissue factor pathway .
Last, uncontrolled placental complement activation by APAs is implicated in fetal loss and growth restriction .
Complications in APS cannot be completely explained by thrombosis alone.
Animal models suggest that effects stem from inflammation rather than thrombosis .
Some investigators hypothesize that APSassociated clotting is triggered as a “second hit” from innate inflammatory immune responses.
These investigators recommend treatment with antiinflammatory agents .
# Adverse Pregnancy Outcomes.
Overall, APAs are associated with higher rates of fetal wastage .
In most early reports that describe these outcomes, however, women were included because they had repeated adverse outcomes.
Both antibody prevalence and miscarriage are common—recall that the incidence of APAs in the general obstetrical population is about 5 percent and early miscarriage approximates 20 percent of call conceptions.
Accordingly, current data are too limited to conclude the exact risks for adverse effects of these antibodies on pregnancy outcomes.
Fetal deaths, however, are more characteristic with APS than are first-trimester miscarriages (Garcia, 2018; Roque, 2004).
When otherwise unexplained fetal deaths are examined, the data are mixed.
One study measured ACA levels in 309 pregnancies with fetal death and found no differences in their frequency compared with levels in 618 normal pregnancies .
In another study of women with recurrent pregnancy loss, those with APAs had an increased rate of preterm delivery .
In a case-control study of 582 stillbirths and 1547 live births, a three- to fivefold higher risk for stillbirth was found in women with elevated ACA and anti-β2 glycoprotein-I levels .
In women with APAs, adverse outcomes are more common in the presence of: (1) all three classic APA types, (2) comorbid SLE or systemic autoimmune diseases, and (3) prior thrombosis and pregnancy morbidity.
Logistic regression found the probability of pregnancy failure was 93 percent with two or more APA types but was 63 percent for those with only one .
# Thrombosis Prevention in Pregnancy.
Because of study heterogeneity, current treatment recommendations for women with APAs can be confusing.
Therapy is directed at thrombosis prevention.
As discussed, APAs are immunoglobulins that may be of G, M, or A classes.
Those directed against the phospholipids (PL) are termed GPL, MPL, and APL, respectively.
During testing,
these are reported as semiquantified phospholipid binding-unit levels and expressed as negative, low-positive, medium-positive, or high-positive .
As discussed in Chapter 55 (p. 979), women with prior thromboembolic events who have APAs are at risk for recurrence in subsequent pregnancies.
For these women, prophylactic anticoagulation with heparin throughout pregnancy and for 6 weeks postpartum is recommended .
For those without prior thromboembolic events, recommendations for management vary and are listed in Table 55-5 (p. 984).
Some acceptable schemes include close antepartum maternal observation with or without prophylactic or intermediate-dose heparin, and then some form of postpartum anticoagulation for 6 weeks.
Sciascia and coworkers (2016) have presented preliminary salutary results with hydroxychloroquine treatment.
This currently is considered investigational (Garcia, 2018; Latino, 2020).
Several researchers have questioned the need for heparin for women with APAs but no history of thrombosis .
Although this is less clear, some recommend that women be treated if they have medium- or highpositive ACA titers or LAC activity and a prior second- or third-trimester fetal death not attributable to other causes (Dizon-Townson, 1998; Lockshin, 1995).
Others report that women with recurrent early pregnancy loss and medium- or high-positive titers of antibodies may benefit from therapy .
Due to the risk of fetal-growth abnormalities and stillbirth, serial sonographic assessment of fetal growth and antepartum testing in the third trimester is recommended (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019a, 2021a,b).
# Specific Therapy in Pregnancy.
Other agents are used to treat gravidas that have APS but no prior thromboembolic event.
Aspirin, in doses of 60 to 80 mg orally daily, blocks conversion of arachidonic acid to thromboxane A2 while sparing prostacyclin production.
Thromboxane A2 usually causes platelet aggregation and vasoconstriction, and prostacyclin has the opposite effect.
The only major side effect from low-dose aspirin is a slight risk of small-vessel bleeding during surgical procedures.
Low-dose aspirin does not reduce adverse pregnancy outcomes in women who have APAs but who lack the complete APS syndrome .
Thus, its use is recommended for women with SLE or APS (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020b; Rahman, 2020).
Unfractionated heparin is given subcutaneously in dosages of 5000 to 10,000 units every 12 hours.
Some prefer low-molecular-weight heparin, such as 40 mg enoxaparin (Lovenox) once daily .
With therapeutic dosing, measurement of heparin levels may be useful because clotting tests can be altered by LAC.
The rationale for heparin therapy is to prevent venous and arterial thrombotic episodes.
Heparin therapy also prevents thrombosis in the microcirculation, including the decidualtrophoblastic interface .
As discussed, heparin binds to β2glycoprotein-I, which coats the syncytiotrophoblast.
This prevents binding of ACAs and anti-β2 glycoprotein-I antibodies to their surfaces, which likely prevents cellular damage .
Heparin also binds to APAs in vitro and likely in vivo.
Aspirin plus heparin therapy is the most effective regimen (de Jesus, 2014; Hamulyák, 2020).
However, despite treatment, 30 percent of women with APS do not achieve a successful outcome .
Heparin therapy is associated with several complications that include bleeding, thrombocytopenia, osteopenia, and osteoporosis.
A description of various heparins and their adverse effects is found in Chapter 55 (p. 983).
Corticosteroids generally should not be used with primary APS—that is, without an associated connective tissue disorder.
For women with SLE or those being treated for APS who develop SLE, corticosteroid therapy is indicated.
In such cases of secondary APS seen with SLE, the dose of prednisone should be maintained at the lowest effective level to prevent flares.
IVIG therapy is controversial and has usually been reserved for women with overt disease—including catastrophic antiphospholipid
syndrome or heparin-induced thrombocytopenia or both .
It is used when other first-line therapies have failed, especially in the setting of preeclampsia and fetal-growth restriction.
IVIG is administered by some in doses of 0.4 g/kg/d for 5 days—total dose of 2 g/kg.
This is repeated monthly, or it is given as a single dose of 1 g/kg each month.
Treatment is expensive, as one course costs more than $10,000.
Tenti and colleagues (2016) found no benefits from adding IVIG to low-dose aspirin and lowmolecular-weight heparin.
One Cochrane review found no improvement in the live-birth rate for IVIG therapy given to women with recurrent pregnancy loss .
Trials are needed before application of this expensive and cumbersome therapy is recommended.
Immunosuppression with hydroxychloroquine is commonly used with low-dose aspirin in the treatment of women with SLE.
This regimen may be beneficial by reducing the risk of thrombosis and improving pregnancy outcomes in women who also have APS (Mekinian, 2015; Sciascia, 2016).
Statins have been examined due to their protective effects on endothelium.
In a small trial in 21 women with APS who developed fetalgrowth restriction or preeclampsia, the addition of pravastatin to low-dose aspirin and low-molecular-weight heparin improved placental blood flow, preeclampsia features, and pregnancy outcomes .
Larger trials are needed before this therapy is recommended.
Described earlier (p. 1114), catastrophic antiphospholipid syndrome is treated aggressively with full anticoagulation, high-dose corticosteroids, plasma exchange, and/or IVIG therapy (Garcia, 2018; Rahman, 2020).
# Treatment Efficacy.
Fetal loss is common in women with untreated APS, and especially in those with LAC positivity.
Even with treatment, recurrent fetal loss rates remain at 20 to 30 percent (Arslan, 2020; Empson, 2005; Ernest, 2011).
Shown in Table 62-6.
are pregnancy outcomes from 750 treated women with primary APS .
Participants were treated with low-dose aspirin and prophylactic low-molecular-weight heparin starting in the first trimester.
Importantly, some women with SLE and APAs have normal pregnancy outcomes without treatment.
It is also emphasized that women with LAC and prior poor pregnancy outcomes have had liveborn neonates without treatment.
TABLE 62-6.
Pregnancy Outcomes (%) in 750 Women Treated for Antiphospholipid Syndrome—the PREGNANTS Study In a manner similar to neonatal lupus syndrome (p. 1113), up to 30 percent of newborns demonstrate passively acquired APAs .
One group found higher rates of learning disabilities in these children .
Another reported a fourfold greater risk for perinatal strokes .
Of 141 newborns followed in a European registry, the rate of preterm birth was 16 percent; low birthweight occurred in 17 percent; and later behavioral abnormalities developed in 4 percent of the children.
There were no cases of neonatal thrombosis .
A 7-year study of 36 pregnancies in 26 women who had APS reported three cases of autism spectrum disorder.
All were associated with persistent neonatal anti-β2 glycoprotein-I IgG antibodies .
Rheumatoid Arthritis.
This chronic inflammatory disease stems from immunological dysfunction, and infiltrating T cells secrete cytokines to cause inflammation, polyarthritis, and systemic symptoms.
The cardinal feature is inflammatory synovitis that usually involves the peripheral joints.
The disease has a propensity for cartilage destruction, bony erosions, and joint deformities.
Pain, aggravated by movement, is accompanied by swelling and tenderness.
Extraarticular manifestations include rheumatoid nodules, vasculitis, and pleuropulmonary symptoms.
Other complaints are fatigue, anorexia, and depression.
The American College of Rheumatology has published diagnostic criteria .
The worldwide prevalence of rheumatoid arthritis is 0.5 to 1 percent, women are affected three times more often than men, and peak onset is from 25 to 55 years .
There is a genetic predisposition, and heritability is estimated at 15 to 30 percent .
Genome-wide associated studies have identified
more than 30 loci involved in rheumatoid arthritis pathogenesis (Kurkó, 2013).
Class II major histocompatibility complex molecule HLA-DR4 and HLA-DRB1 alleles also show an association (McInnes, 2011; Shah, 2018).
Pregnancy provides a protection against rheumatoid arthritis development, and this may be related to HLAdisparate fetal microchimerism (Förger, 2020; Guthrie, 2010).
# Management.
Treatment is directed at pain relief, inflammation reduction, protection of articular structures, and preservation of function.
Physical and occupational therapy and self-care instructions are essential.
Aspirin and other NSAIDs nonspecifically inhibit both cyclooxygenase 1 (COX-1), which is an enzyme critical to normal platelet function, and COX2, which mediates inflammatory response mechanisms.
However, in one systematic review, a small increased rate of cardiac malformations was found in newborns exposed to NSAIDs in the first trimester .
In addition, NSAIDs are associated with early spontaneous abortions, ductus arteriosus constriction, and neonatal pulmonary hypertension .
Another potential side effect of chronic NSAID therapy is gastritis with acute bleeding.
Thus, risks versus benefits of these medications must be considered.
Glucocorticoid therapy in low to moderate doses is given to achieve more rapid symptom control.
Of these, prednisone, 7.5 mg orally daily for the first 2 years of active disease, substantively reduces progressive joint erosions .
Until recently, NSAIDs were the cornerstone of therapy, but they do not retard disease progression.
The American College of Rheumatology recommends several disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs) that may reduce or prevent joint damage .
According to Shah and St. Clair (2018), methotrexate has become the preferred DMARD outside of pregnancy.
NSAIDs thus are important in pregnancy because methotrexate and leflunomide are contraindicated (Chap. 8, pp. 151–152).
In one review of drug exposure, a fourth of women with rheumatoid arthritis took a DMARD within 6 months of conception .
Of unplanned exposures during pregnancy, 4 percent of 393 pregnant women were given a category D or X medication—methotrexate was the most common at 2.9 percent.
Sulfasalazine and hydroxychloroquine are safe for use in pregnancy (Briggs, 2022; Partlett, 2011).
These, combined with relatively low-dose prednisone—7.5 to 20 mg daily—usually successfully treat flares.
Biological DMARDs have revolutionized rheumatoid arthritis treatment.
These include the tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α) inhibitors infliximab, adalimumab, golimumab, certolizumab, and etanercept .
Their use in pregnancy is limited, but they appear to be safe for the fetus .
In one review, 13 percent of 393 pregnant women were given a biological cytokine-inhibiting DMARD—primarily etanercept .
In another review of 300 exposures, no fetal effects were noted .
A prospective study of 38 pregnant women found similar results .
In 74 women exposed to adalimumab during pregnancy, no risks were identified .
Little is known regarding the pregnancy effects of anakinra, an interleukin 1 receptor antagonist, or of rituximab, an antagonist to the B-cell CD20 antigen.
Other biologics are abatacept, tocilizumab, and tofacitinib.
# Pregnancy and Rheumatoid Arthritis.
In up to 70 percent of women with rheumatoid arthritis, disease will improve during pregnancy (Raine, 2020; Shah, 2018).
Some studies suggest this may be due to regulatory T-cell alterations (Förger, 2020).
Even so, some women develop disease during pregnancy, and others become worse.
A downside to this respite during pregnancy is that postpartum exacerbation occurs in 40 to 50 percent of women (Eudy, 2018; Jethwa, 2019).
This may stem from postpartum alterations in innate immunity (Häupl, 2008b).
Some studies report a protective effect of pregnancy against developing new-onset rheumatoid arthritis.
In a case-control study of 88 affected women, pregnancy provided a degree of protection long term, but the likelihood of new-onset rheumatoid arthritis was increased sixfold
during the first 3 postpartum months .
Pikwer and colleagues (2009) reported a significant reduction in the risk of subsequent arthritis in women who breastfed longer than 12 months.
These findings may reflect the interference of sex hormones with several putative processes involved in arthritis pathogenesis, including immunoregulation (Förger, 2020; Häupl, 2008a,b).
First, Unger and associates (1983) reported that amelioration of rheumatoid arthritis correlated with serum levels of pregnancy-associated alpha2-glycoprotein.
This compound has immunosuppressive properties.
Second, Nelson and coworkers (1993) noted that disease improvement was associated with a disparity in HLA class II antigens between mother and fetus.
They suggested that the maternal immune response to paternal HLA antigens may play a role in pregnancy-induced remission of arthritis.
In addition to monocyte activations, there also may be T-lymphocyte activation (Förger, 2020).
Fertility is diminished in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, and adverse pregnancy outcomes are increased.
Kishore and colleagues (2019) reported pregnancy outcomes from nearly 32,000 women with rheumatoid arthritis.
Compared with unaffected women, those with rheumatoid arthritis had significantly greater rates of hypertensive diseases, preterm birth, hemorrhage, and fetal-growth restriction.
# Juvenile Rheumatoid Arthritis.
This group of diseases is the most frequent cause of chronic arthritis in children and persists into adulthood.
In 76 pregnancies of 51 affected Norwegian women, pregnancy had no effects on clinical presentation, but disease activity usually became quiescent or remained so during pregnancy (Østensen, 1991).
Similar to rheumatoid arthritis, postpartum flares were common.
Joint deformities often developed in these women, and 15 of 20 cesarean deliveries were done for contracted pelves or joint prostheses.
Results from a summary of 39 Polish women with juvenile rheumatoid arthritis were similar .
This arthritis portends few adverse pregnancy outcomes.
The risk for preterm birth is elevated, but fetal development is normal (Mohamed, 2016; Rom, 2014; Wallenius, 2014).
In a study of 1807 births, Remaeus and associates (2017) reported increased incidences of preterm birth, fetalgrowth restriction, and preeclampsia.
Disease severity in early pregnancy was predictive of preterm delivery and fetal-growth restriction in one cohort study .
And, patients with low disease activity scores in the first trimester are likely to have low disease activity or remission in the third trimester .
If the cervical spine is involved, particular attention is warranted during pregnancy.
Subluxation is common, and pregnancy, at least theoretically, predisposes to this because of joint laxity.
Importantly, there are anesthesia concerns during endotracheal intubation.
Systemic Sclerosis—Scleroderma.
This is a chronic multisystem connective tissue disorder of unknown etiology.
It is characterized by microvascular damage; inflammation from immune system activation; and excessive deposition of collagen in the skin, lungs, heart, gastrointestinal tract, and kidneys.
It is uncommon, displays a 5to-1 female dominance, and typically affects those aged 30 to 50 years (Clark, 2020; Varga, 2018).
This strong prevalence of scleroderma in women and its greater incidence in the years following childbirth give credence to the hypothesis that microchimerism is involved as discussed earlier (p. 1109) .
Artlett and associates (1998) demonstrated Y-chromosomal DNA in almost half of women with systemic sclerosis compared with only 4 percent of controls.
Rak and coworkers (2009) identified male microchimerism in peripheral blood mononuclear cells more frequently in women with limited versus diffuse scleroderma.
# Clinical Course.
The hallmark is overproduction of normal collagen.
Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis is the more benign form and progresses slowly.
With diffuse cutaneous systemic sclerosis, skin fibrosis advances rapidly and is followed by gastrointestinal tract fibrosis, especially the
distal esophagus .
Pulmonary interstitial fibrosis along with vascular changes may cause pulmonary hypertension, which develops in 15 percent of patients.
Antinuclear antibodies such as those listed in Table 62-1 are found in 95 percent of patients, and immunoincompetence often develops.
Raynaud phenomenon, which is typified by cold-induced, episodic, rapidly reversible digital ischemia, is seen in 95 percent of patients.
There also may be swelling of the distal extremities and face.
Symptoms from esophageal involvement, especially fullness and epigastric burning pain, occur in half of patients.
Pulmonary involvement is frequent and causes dyspnea.
The 10-year cumulative survival rate is 70 percent in those with pulmonary fibrosis, and pulmonary arterial hypertension is the main cause of death (Clark, 2020; Varga, 2018).
Women with limited cutaneous disease such as the CREST syndrome—calcinosis, Raynaud phenomenon, esophageal involvement, sclerodactyly, and telangiectasia—have milder disease.
Overlap syndrome refers to systemic sclerosis with features of other connective tissue disorders.
Mixed connective tissue disease is a term used for the syndrome involving features of SLE, systemic sclerosis, polymyositis, rheumatoid arthritis, and high titers of anti-ribonucleoprotein (RNP) antibodies .
The disorder is also termed undifferentiated connective tissue disease (Radin, 2020; Zucchi, 2020).
Although systemic sclerosis is incurable, treatment directed at end-organ involvement can sometimes relieve symptoms and improve function.
Renal involvement and hypertension are often comorbid.
At times, ACE inhibitors may be required for blood pressure control despite their known teratogenicity.
Obliterative vasculopathy of the renal cortical arteries characterizes scleroderma renal crisis, which develops in up to a fourth of these patients.
This leads to renal failure and malignant hypertension.
Interstitial restrictive lung disease is common and frequently becomes life threatening.
Associated pulmonary hypertension is treated with bosentan or sildenafil .
# Pregnancy and Systemic Sclerosis.
The prevalence of scleroderma in pregnancy approximates 1 case in 22,000 pregnancies .
If baseline function is good, these women usually have stable disease during gestation.
As perhaps expected, pregnancy aggravates dysphagia and reflux esophagitis .
Dysphagia results from loss of esophageal motility due to neuromuscular dysfunction.
A lower amplitude or disappearance of peristaltic waves in the lower two thirds of the esophagus is seen using manometry.
Symptomatic treatment for reflux is described in Chapter 57 (p. 1017).
Women with renal insufficiency and malignant hypertension have a higher incidence of superimposed preeclampsia.
With rapidly worsening renal or cardiac disease, pregnancy termination should be considered.
Renal crisis is uncommon, but it is life threatening, and it does not improve with delivery .
Pulmonary hypertension usually contraindicates pregnancy (Table 52-3, p. 919).
Vaginal delivery may be anticipated, unless the soft tissue thickening wrought by scleroderma produces dystocia requiring cesarean delivery.
Tracheal intubation for general anesthesia has special concerns because of limited ability of these women to open their mouths widely .
Because of esophageal dysfunction, aspiration is also more likely, and neuraxial analgesia is preferable.
Warming the delivery room and intravenous fluids, extra blankets, and socks and gloves are considered to improve impaired circulation from Raynaud phenomenon.
If corticosteroids were used frequently, stress doses of hydrocortisone, described earlier for SLE (p. 1113), are recommended .
Maternal and fetal outcomes correlate with underlying disease severity.
In a review of 214 gravidas with systemic sclerosis, 45 percent had diffuse disease .
Major complications included renal crisis in three and greater rates of preterm birth.
A multicenter study of 109 pregnancies from 25 centers reported increased rates of preterm delivery, fetal-growth restriction, and
very-low-birthweight newborns .
In a review of 307 affected pregnancies, risks for miscarriage, preterm births, and gestational hypertension were increased .
These are likely related to placental abnormalities that include decidual vasculopathy, acute atherosis, and infarcts .
Somewhat related, perinatal outcomes are similar with undifferentiated connective tissue diseases (Radin, 2020; Zucchi, 2020).
Scleroderma may be associated with subfertility (Bernatsky, 2008; Lambe, 2004).
For women who do not choose pregnancy, several reversible contraceptive methods are acceptable.
However, hormonal agents, especially combination oral contraceptives, probably should not be used, especially in women with pulmonary, cardiac, or renal involvement.
Due to the often unrelenting progression of systemic sclerosis, permanent sterilization also is considered.
Vasculitis Syndromes.
Inflammation and damage to blood vessels may be primary or caused by another disease.
Immune-complex deposition is presumed to underlie most cases .
Primary types are listed in Table 62-7 .
Small vessel vasculitides such as granulomatosis with polyangiitis and eosinophilic granulomatosis with polyangiitis have antibodies directed against proteins in the cytoplasmic granules of leukocytes—antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies (ANCA) .
In general, women with a vasculitis syndrome have elevated rates of preterm birth and preeclampsia .
Table 62-7.
Primary Vasculitis Syndromes # Polyarteritis Nodosa.
This necrotizing vasculitis of small and medium-sized arteries is characterized clinically by myalgia, neuropathy, gastrointestinal disorders, hypertension, and renal disease .
A third of cases are associated with hepatitis B antigenemia .
Symptoms are nonspecific, and fever, weight loss, and malaise are present in more than half of cases.
Diagnosis is made by biopsy, and treatment is high-dose prednisone plus cyclophosphamide.
Vasculitis due to hepatitis B antigenemia responds to antivirals, glucocorticosteroids, and plasma exchange .
Only a few reports describe polyarteritis nodosa associated with pregnancy.
Of 12 affected gravidas, polyarteritis first manifested during pregnancy in seven, and it was rapidly fatal by 6 weeks postpartum .
The diagnosis was not made until autopsy in six of the seven women.
Four women continued pregnancy, which resulted in one stillborn and three successful outcomes.
# Granulomatosis with Polyangiitis—Wegener.
Granulomatosis This is a small-vessel necrotizing granulomatous vasculitis affecting the upper and lower respiratory tract and kidney .
Disease frequently includes sinusitis and nasal disease (90 percent); pulmonary infiltrates, cavities, or nodules (85 percent); glomerulonephritis (75 percent); and musculoskeletal lesions (65 percent) .
At least 90 percent have polyangiitis .
It is uncommon and usually encountered after age 50.
Koukoura and associates (2008) reviewed 36 cases in association with pregnancy and found a higher preterm birth rate.
In another report, a second woman had disease-related pneumonitis, but pregnancy did not appear to affect disease activity .
Because subglottic stenosis is found in up to a fourth of patients, the anesthesiology service is ideally consulted antepartum .
Therapeutic options are limited by teratogenicity and fetotoxicity .
Corticosteroids are standard treatment, but azathioprine, cyclosporine, and IVIG therapy may also be used.
For severe disease in the late second or third trimester, cyclophosphamide in combination with prednisolone is highly effective.
Rituximab is also approved for this disorder and appears to be safe for the fetus .
# Takayasu Arteritis.
Also called pulseless disease, this is a chronic inflammatory arteritis affecting large vessels .
Unlike temporal arteritis, which develops almost exclusively after age 55, the onset of Takayasu arteritis is almost always before age 40.
It is associated with abnormal angiography of the upper aorta and its main branches and with upper extremity vascular impairment.
Death usually results from congestive heart failure or
cerebrovascular events.
Computed tomography or magnetic resonance angiography can detect this disorder before the development of severe vascular compromise.
Takayasu arteritis may respond symptomatically to corticosteroid therapy, however, it is not curative.
Surgical bypass or angioplasty improves survival rates.
Comorbid severe renovascular hypertension, cardiac involvement, or pulmonary hypertension worsen pregnancy prognosis (Comarmond, 2020; Singh, 2015).
Hypertension is relatively common and should be carefully controlled.
Blood pressure is most accurately measured in the lower extremity.
Overall, the prognosis for pregnancy is good .
A study of 43 pregnancies in 33 women with Takayasu arteritis reported that half had complications .
Authors described an increased risk of pregnancy-related hypertension and preeclampsia but overall favorable maternal and fetal outcomes.
A review from Comarmond and colleagues (2020) cites a 5-percent life-threatening cardiovascular complication rate.
Involvement of the abdominal aorta portends worse perinatal outcome .
Vaginal delivery is preferred, and epidural analgesia has been advocated for labor and delivery.
# Other Vasculitides.
Behçet disease is rare, and its prevalence approximates 1 case per 100,000 births .
In one series of 298 pregnancies in 94 affected women, rates of miscarriage and smaller babies were higher than those in healthy controls .
Although greater risks for preeclampsia, preterm delivery, and venous thromboembolism are reported, pregnancy is not contraindicated (Elliot, 2019; Merlino, 2020).
Formerly Churg-Strauss vasculitis, eosinophilic granulomatosis with polyangiitis is rare in pregnancy .
One case report described a pregnant woman who responded to IVIG therapy .
Another presented an affected 35-year-old woman at term whose necrotizing vasculitis involved the heart, and she subsequently underwent cardiac transplantation .
Edwards (2015) described one woman who developed postpartum relapses of this vasculitis in each of two pregnancies.
Henoch-Schönlein purpura is uncommon after childhood.
Characteristic signs of the disorder include purpuric rash, arthralgia, abdominal pain, and gastrointestinal bleeding.
In one review of 20 pregnancies complicated by this vasculitis, cutaneous lesions and arthralgias were present in three fourths and in approximately one half, respectively .
HenochSchönlein purpura responds well to corticosteroid therapy, and pregnancy outcomes are generally good .
Inflammatory Myopathies.
These are acquired and potentially treatable causes of skeletal muscle weakness with a prevalence of 14 to 32 cases in 100,000 persons .
Three major groups are polymyositis, dermatomyositis, and inclusion-body myositis, which all present with progressive asymmetrical muscle weakness.
They have a variable association with connective tissue diseases, malignancy, drugs, systemic autoimmune disease such as Crohn disease, and viral, bacterial, and parasitic infections.
Polymyositis is a subacute inflammatory myopathy that is frequently associated with one of the autoimmune connective tissue disorders (Bitencourt, 2020; Munira, 2020).
Dermatomyositis manifests as a characteristic rash accompanying or preceding weakness.
Laboratory findings include elevated muscle enzyme levels in serum and an abnormal electromyogram.
Confirmation is by biopsy, which shows perivascular and perimysial inflammatory infiltrates, vasculitis, and muscle fiber degeneration.
It usually develops alone but can overlap with systemic sclerosis or mixed connective tissue disease.
Prevailing theories suggest that the syndromes are caused by viral infections, autoimmune disorders, or both.
Importantly, approximately 15 percent of adults who develop dermatomyositis have an associated malignant tumor.
The timing of myositis and tumor appearance may be separated by several years.
The most common sites of associated cancer are breast, lung, stomach, and ovary.
The disease usually responds to high-dose corticosteroid therapy, immunosuppressive drugs such as azathioprine or methotrexate, or
IVIG (Dalakas, 2012; Linardaki, 2011).
Experiences in pregnancy are garnered mostly from case series and reviews.
One cohort of 17 gravidas with polymyositis/dermatomyositis had higher rates of hypertension (23 percent), antepartum hemorrhage (11 percent), cesarean delivery (88 percent), and preterm birth (35 percent) compared with unaffected pregnant women .
In another series of 60 women with dermatomyositis and 38 with polymyositis, 80 percent had no adverse effect on their disease.
Similar results have been reported by others (Missumi, 2015; Pinal-Fernandez, 2014).
Pregnancy outcome is related to dermatomyositis activity, and new-onset disease is particularly aggressive .
Hereditary Connective Tissue Disorders.
Numerous inherited mutations involve genes that encode for structural proteins of bone, skin, cartilage, blood vessels, and basement membranes.
Although connective tissues contain many complex macromolecules such as elastin and more than 30 proteoglycans, the most common constituents are fibrillar collagen types I, II, and III.
Various mutations, some recessively and some dominantly inherited, result in clinical syndromes that include Marfan and Ehlers-Danlos syndromes, osteogenesis imperfecta, chondrodysplasias, and epidermolysis bulla.
Of concern during pregnancy is the predilection for these disorders to result in aortic aneurysms .
# Marfan Syndrome.
This is an autosomal dominant connective tissue disorder that has a population prevalence of 1 case in 3000 to 5000 .
Marfan syndrome affects both sexes equally.
The syndrome is due to abnormal fibrillin—a constituent of elastin—caused by any of several different mutations in the FBN1 gene .
Located on chromosome 15q21, the FBN1 gene has a high mutation rate.
The lack of distinct genotypephenotype correlation and large clinical variability limits the ability to predict disease severity in progeny.
Currently, preimplantation genetic testing and prenatal diagnosis are limited to the 80 percent of cases in which the mutation in the FBN1 gene is known .
In severe disease, the elastic lamina in the media of the aorta shows degeneration.
This predisposes to aortic dilation or dissecting aneurysm, which appears more commonly during pregnancy (Curry, 2014; Roman, 2016).
Marfan syndrome was found to underlie 65 percent of cases of aortic dissection in 27 pregnant women .
Marfan syndrome complicating pregnancy is discussed in more detail in Chapter 52 (p. 936).
# Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome.
This disease is characterized by various connective tissue changes, including skin hyperelasticity.
Its prevalence is 7 cases per 100,000 births .
Several disease types vary based on skin, joint, or other tissue involvement.
In the more severe types, rupture of any of several arteries can cause either stroke or bleeding.
Some types are autosomal dominant, some recessive, and some X-linked .
Types I, II, and III are autosomally dominant, and each accounts for approximately 30 percent of cases.
Type IV is uncommon but is known to predispose to preterm delivery, great-vessel rupture, postpartum bleeding, and uterine rupture .
In most, the underlying molecular defect affects collagen or procollagen.
In general, women with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome have a higher frequency of preterm rupture of membranes, preterm delivery, antepartum and postpartum hemorrhage, placenta previa, and cervical insufficiency (Hurst, 2014; Spiegel, 2020).
Several cases of spontaneous uterine rupture have been described .
Tissue fragility makes episiotomy repair and cesarean delivery difficult.
A maternal and fetal death from spontaneous rupture of the right iliac artery has been reported .
In another case, a newborn was found to have multiple congenital skull fractures and intracranial hemorrhage caused by Ehlers-Danlos type VIIC .
# Osteogenesis Imperfecta.
This disorder has a prevalence of 1 case in 20,000 births for type I and 1 case in 60,000 for type II .
It is characterized by brittle bones, and affected patients often have blue sclerae, hearing loss, multiple prior bone fractures, and dental abnormalities.
There are up to 15 subtypes based on the causative gene and clinical picture, which ranges from mild to severe .
Genetic inheritance includes autosomal dominant, autosomal recessive, and sporadic patterns.
Type I is the mildest form, and the typical mutation affects the COL1A1 gene .
Type II is typically lethal in utero.
Women with osteogenesis imperfecta, most commonly type I, may have successful pregnancies.
However, risks include fractures, complications related to scoliosis with restrictive lung disease, micrognathia, brittle teeth, an unstable cervical spine, uterine rupture, and cephalopelvic disproportion.
A retrospective cohort of 295 women with osteogenesis imperfecta found greater risks of antepartum hemorrhage, placental abruption, fetal-growth restriction, congenital malformations, and preterm birth .
It is not unusual for affected women to enter pregnancy with 20 to 30 prior fractures.
Most require minimal treatment other than management of the fractures and consideration of bisphosphonates to decrease bone loss.
Depending on the type of osteogenesis imperfecta, the fetus may be affected and may also suffer fractures in utero or during delivery.
Preimplantation genetic testing and prenatal diagnosis is available in many situations, if desired.
In utero stem cell therapy is being evaluated .